Guide to the Harry F. Shaw, Jr. Papers, 1963-1973 AIS.1974.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Subject Files, IV.
  - Labor (Box 4, Folder 160)
    - Bonnell, V. and Reich, M., "Workers and the American Economy: Data on the Labor Force," prepared to provide radicals with a source of stats, 1969; 1.
    - Leaflets on strikes in the South, 2.
    - Leaflets on demos and strikes in Pittsburgh, 3.
    - Correspondence thanking supporters of the UE Strike by P. Jennings, UE President Asserts workers should not be blamed for inflation, 4.
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets, brochures, etc., 5.
    - West Virginia Centennial Commission One Hundred Years with West Virginia Labor, 6.
    - Detroit Black Caucus: UAW/Black Workers, 7.
  - McCarthy Campaign (West Virginia) - Pamphlets, brochures, leaflets statements, correspondence, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - McGovern Campaign - Correspondence, leaflets, brochures Western Pennsylvania Citizens for McGovern Newsletter, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Mining (Box 4, Folder 163)
    - Statement: "The Disabled Miner's View of the Compensation Commission", 1.
    - Grievance petition on rotation of shifts Humphrey Mine No. 7 (Umpire's decision attached), March 27, 1969; 2.
    - Pleading: "State of West Virginia vs. 'Mother' Jones, et al.", 3.
  - Morgantown, West Virginia - Open Housing, welfare rights, and pollution of the environment (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Morgantown - Citizens concerned about the war in Vietnam (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Names of people active in reform activities with theminers and mountain people (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Political Realignment - Max, S., Ireland, D. and Williams, J., "For a New Coalition: A Strategy for Social Change in America" (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Poor People's Campaign (Box 4, Folder 168)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1.
    - Efforts to enlist students and the universities (a Poor Peoples' University), 2.
    - News releases, April 22 and 29, 1968; 3.
    - Background, plans, and schedule for the march on Washington; address by R. Abernathy and G. Wiley, 4.
    - Fact sheet prepared for the staff of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference regarding poverty in America, 5.
  - Poverty (Box 4, Folder 169)
    - Vista activity in the South, 1.
    - Statement accusing Sen. Byrd of being hostile to the poor, 2.
    - Shriver, Sergeant, Poverty, 3.
    - OEO: The War on Poverty, 4.
  - Race Relations - "Southern Regional Council Events at Orangeburg: A Report based on Study and Interviews in Orangeburg, SC in the Aftermath of Tragedy", by Pat Watters and Weldon Rougeau (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - Race Relations (Box 4, Folder 171)
    - King, Dr. Martin Luther assassination, 1.
    - Calls for White non-violence by the Center for Emergency Support, 2.
    - A Special Report on the Duke Silent Vigil, April 5-11, 1968; 3.
  - Race Relations (Box 4, Folder 172)
    - Articles and unpublished papers, 1.
    - Mitchell, H. H., "Negro Worship and Universal Need", 2.
    - Article on the 1943 Harlem race riots, 3.
    - Segregation within the UMW, 4.
    - "Statement of National Committee for Free Elections in Mississippi: A Proposal for Northern Report", 5.
    - An address to the UEW on the Contribution of Black Americans, 1968; 6.
    - Summary of Report of the Commission on Civil Disorders, 7.
  - Race Relations - Apartheid in South Africa (Box 4, Folder 173)
  - Race Relations - The Black Manifesto adopted at the National Black Economic Development Conference, Detroit, NI, April 26, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - Race Relations - Comments on the causes of racial disorders (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Race Relations - Miscellaneous articles, leaflets, and pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - South Bend Project - A Midwest coalition to combat war, racism, and repression (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Strip Mining (Box 4, Folder 178)
    - "Strip Mining in Ohio Under Attack," a booklet published by the Cleveland Plain Dealer, 1.
    - Leaflets, 2.
    - Bills presented to the West Virginia Legislature related to strip mining, 3.
  - Underground Newspapers regarding the South (Box 4, Folder 179)
    - List with addresses, 1.
    - Liberation News Service: Correspondence, advertisement explaining function, facilities, and seeking subscribers, June 1968; 2.
  - University of Pittsburgh (Box 4, Folder 180)
    - May Day address, May 1, 1970; 1.
    - Leaflet: "Socialist Perspectives for the 1970's," Revolutionary Socialist Union, 2.
  - Vietnam War - "The Cambridge Vote on Vietnam: A Report of an Anti-War Project based among Working Class People in Cambridge, Mass", 1967 (Box 4, Folder 181)
  - Vietnam War (Box 4, Folder 182)
    Leaflets in protest centering on the themes of: Hiroshima Day, labor against the war, taxes, student mobilization, a public letter from two peace corporation volunteers against the war, women's peace groups, out now.
  - Vietnam War (Box 4, Folder 183)
    - Statements of protest by: US Senators, clergymen, military leaders, anti-war organizations, 1.
    - Statement by Project Purse strings urging Congress not to appropriate money for the war, 2.
    - Law Students Against the War, 3.
  - Vietnam War (Box 4, Folder 184)
    - Papers and publications, 1.
    - Concerned Citizens for Peace, a public poll showing disenchantment with the war, 2.
    - Cothran, "Songs for the Vietnam War", 3.
    - Duncan, D., "A 'Green Beret' Blasts the War", 4.
    - CBS News public Opinion Survey, 5.
    - Fleming, D.F., "What is our Role in East Asia?", 6.
    - King, M.L., Jr., et al., "Speak on the War...", 7.
    - Liberman, R., M.D., "Medical and Social Consequences of the War... ", 8.
    - Lin Piao, "Long Live the Victory of the People's War", 9.
    - Schesch, Adam, "An Outlining History of Vietnam", 10.
    - "US Imperialists' Policy in South Vietnam", 11.
  - Washington, DC (Box 4, Folder 185)
    - Home Rule, 1.
    - Position of Sen. H. Byrd, 2.
  - West Virginia Peoples' Meeting - Statement protesting a cutback on Aid to Dependent Children (Box 4, Folder 186)
  - Campus Ministry (Box 5, Folder 187)
    - Consultation on Ecumenical Team Ministry - Correspondence, program, speeches, May 20-21, 1968; 1.
    - Leaflets, brochures, etc. detailing the various activities of the campus Ministry, 2.
  - Coal Mine Health and Safety Conference, November 20-22, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 188)
    - Correspondence and program, 1.
    - Address by Rep. K. Hechler, "The Fight for Coal Mine Health and Safety", 2.
    - Address by Frank G. Tsutras, Administrative Assistant to Rep. James Kee in regarding the legislative history of coal mine health, safety, and compensation laws, 3.
  - Festival of Ideas (Box 5, Folder 189)
    - Correspondence, minutes, programs, 1.
    - Address by Rep. K. Hechler, "Medievalism in the Mines", 2.
  - Leaflets - Various campus activities: anti-war, discussion topics for the Round Table, the Free University, anti-SDS group, faculty home seminars, open housing in Morgantown (Box 5, Folder 190)
  - Mine Safety Conference, April 25-26, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 191)
    - Program, 1.
    - Address by L. J. Pnakovoch, "The UMW Safety Program and its Present Position on Safety", 2.
    - WVU Law students, "Mine Health and Safety Project", 3.
  - Mountaineer Freedom Party (Box 5, Folder 192)
    - Constitution, 1.
    - Statements of philosophies, aims, and goals, 2.
  - Mountaineer Freedom Party (Box 5, Folder 193)
    - Steering Committee, 1.
    - Membership role, 2.
    - Tabulation of the February 11, 1970 student election, 3.
    - Leaflets regarding Vietnam, 4.
    - Correspondence, 1968-1970; 5.
  - H. Shaw's pay stubs - Checking account receipt WVU Emergency Black Committee (Box 5, Folder 194)
  - Speeches, statements, position papers (Box 5, Folder 195)
    Topics: antiwar, "Changes in the Relative Economic Status on Nonwhites," anti-activist league, student worker alliance (a statement by Linda Nyden), VISTA, statement by the Young Democratic Club of why it refused support to the Humphrey Muskie ticket and a statement by the Student Legislature protesting proposed changes in the student code.
  - Student Action for Appalachian Progress (Box 5, Folder 196)
    A program organized by WVU students to relate to and assist in solving the poverty and illiteracy problems the area around Morgantown
    - Background statement, 1.
    - Proposals and guides for training volunteer tutors, 2.
    - Program, 1968; 3.
    - Correspondence from the tutorial assistance center, July 1, 1967; 4.
    - Directory for SAAP volunteers, 5.
  - Students for a Democratic Society (Box 5, Folder 197)
    - Correspondence, including correspondence with H. Shaw, 1967-1969; 1.
    - Shaw's address to Morgantown Rotary Club, report in Rotary newsletter, 2.
    - Leaflets, 3.
    - SDS activities on WVU campus, 4.
    - Membership roll and mailing list, 5.
  - The Non-Group - Newsletters, 1-4 (Box 5, Folder 198)
  - University Christian Movement (Box 5, Folder 199)
    - Articles of Operation, 1.
    - State Conference, November 10-12, 1967; 2.
    - State Conference (organized by H. Shaw), March 21-23, 1969; 3.
    - Correspondence, 1968-1969; 4.
    - Program, 5.
  - Yablonski (Box 5, Folder 200)
    - Bulletin for the funeral mass at the Immaculate Conception Church, Washington, Pa., January 9, 1970
    - Statement of commendation by Rep. Ken Hechler in the Congressional Record, March 3, 1970
- Publications, V.
  The Publications series includes a variety of publications collected by Shaw.
  - African Agenda: A Voice of Afro-American Opinion (Box 5, Folder 201)
  - Alice: The Blacksburg Free Press, Vol. 3, Nos. 5-6 (Box 5, Folder 202)
  - A Lump of Sugar, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-2 (Box 5, Folder 203)
  - American Dialog, Vol. 3, No. 3; Vol. 6, No. 1. (Box 5, Folder 204)
  - American Institute of Marxist Studies Newsletter, Vol. VI, No. 1-6 and Vol. VII, No. 1 (Box 5, Folder 205)
  - American Lung Association Bulletin, October 1973 (Box 5, Folder 206)
  - Appalachian View, Fall 1968 (Box 5, Folder 207)
  - Appalachian Advance, Vol. 3, No. 2 (Box 5, Folder 208)
  - Appalachian Lookout, Vol. I, Nos. 1-2, 4, 6 (Box 5, Folder 209)
  - The Appalachian South, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-4 and Vol. 2, No. 1 (Box 5, Folder 210)
  - Appalachian Student Press, March 1969 (Box 5, Folder 211)
  - Appalachian Student Press (WVA/SSOC Newsletter) (Box 5, Folder 212)
  - Beacon Hi Lites, Vol. 1, No. 2 (Box 5, Folder 213)
  - Black Bung Bulletin (West Virginia Black Lung Association Newsletter), April 1970-June 1972 (Box 5, Folder 214)
    Twelve issues in total
  - The Bluefield Other (Box 5, Folder 215)
  - The Boston Student Mobilizer (Box 5, Folder 216)
  - Catholic Worker, Vol. 32 No. 9; Vol. 33 Nos.1-7, 9-10, 12; Vol. 34 No. 5 (Box 5, Folder 217)
  - Citizens to Abolish Strip Hioing, February 1971 (Box 5, Folder 218)
  - Coal Mining and Processing, Vol. 7, Nos. 3, 5 (Box 5, Folder 219)
  - Coal Patrol, Nos. 1-3, 7-11, 13-27 (Box 5, Folder 220)
  - Communist viewpoint, Bulletin of the Wisconsin Communist Party, Vol. 2, Nos. 4-5 (Box 5, Folder 221)
  - Concern, Vol. 6, No. 19; Vol. 9, Nos. 4, 9 (Box 5, Folder 222)
  - Counterattack, New Haven Panther Defense Committee (Box 5, Folder 223)
  - Crisis, Vol. 1, No. 4 (Box 5, Folder 224)
  - Dateline Ithaca, No. 24 (Box 5, Folder 225)
  - The Eagle Eye, Vol. 1, Nos. 2-3, 5-11 (Box 5, Folder 226)
  - El Malcriado, Vol. I, Nos. 52-66; Vol. II, Nos. 2-7, 9-10, 12, 19, 22; Vol. III, No. 2 (Box 5, Folder 227)
  - Fateh, Vol. 2, Nos. 11-13 (Box 5, Folder 228)
  - The First Issue, layout copy (Box 5, Folder 229)
  - For Final Victory: Bulletin of the World Youth Action Campaign, Nos. 1, 3, 5 (Box 5, Folder 230)
  - The 'Forgot nest', May 1965 (Box 5, Folder 231)
  - The Free Forum, Vol. 1, No. 2 (Box 5, Folder 232)
  - The Great Speckled Bird, Vol. 1, No. 3 (Box 5, Folder 233)
  - I'm All Right (Box 5, Folder 234)
  - Independent Socialist Bulletin, No. 5 (Box 5, Folder 235)
  - In Touch & Involved, Vol. 1, No. 2 (Box 5, Folder 236)
  - Labor Today, April 1970 (Box 6, Folder 237)
  - Latin American News Letter, No. 67, April 1968 (Box 6, Folder 238)
  - Liberator, March 1970 (Box 6, Folder 239)
  - Mayday, No. 3 (Box 6, Folder 240)
  - The Miners Election Special, November 1970 (Box 6, Folder 241)
  - Miners' Gazette, Vol. 1, No. 1 (Box 6, Folder 242)
  - Miners' International News, Nos. 1, 2, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 243)
  - The Miner's Voice, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-2; Vol. 2, Nos. 2 (Note: both October and December 1970 are marked Vol. 2, No. 2), 3-5, 7, 8, and 10 (Box 6, Folder 244)
  - Mobilizer, Vol. 2, No. 2 (Box 6, Folder 245)
  - Mountain Life & Work, October-November 1970 (Box 6, Folder 246)
  - The Mountain Messenger, Vol. 2, No. 2 (Box 6, Folder 247)
  - National Strike Information Center Newsletter #11 (Box 6, Folder 248)
  - New Politics News, Nos. 3-4 and two unnumbered volumes (Box 6, Folder 249)
  - The New South Student, Vol. 2, No. 6; Vol. 4, Nos. 1-3, 6; Vol. 5, Nos. 1, 5-6; Vol. 6, No. 1 (Box 6, Folder 250)
  - News & Letters, Vol. 14, No. 5 (Box 6, Folder 251)
  - News Notes of the Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors, Vol. 17, No. 2; Vol. 18, Nos. 4-5; Vol. 19, Nos. 1,3; Vol. 20, Nos. 1,3 (Box 6, Folder 252)
  - Nola Express, Vol. 1, No. 18 (Box 6, Folder 253)
  - The Objector, No. 3 (Box 6, Folder 254)
  - Ohio Peace Action News, Vol. 1, No. 1 (Box 6, Folder 255)
  - On The Line, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-2 (Box 6, Folder 256)
  - Orange, No. 2 (Box 6, Folder 257)
  - Palestine Resistance Bulletin, No. 1, August 1970 (Box 6, Folder 258)
  - The Peace Times, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-2 (Box 6, Folder 259)
  - Party Affairs, Vol. 3, Nos. 1-2, 4-11; Vol. 4, Nos. 2, 5; Vol. 5, Nos. 1 (Box 6, Folder 260)
  - Peacework, Vols. 3-7, October 1970 - January 1971 (Box 6, Folder 261)
  - Peoples' Appalachia, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-6 (Box 6, Folder 262)
  - Phoenix, Vol. 1, Nos. 4-6 (Box 6, Folder 263)
  - Portlite: Bulletin of the Waterfront Communist, September 1970 and March 1971 (Box 6, Folder 264)
  - Revolutionary Youth Movement (Box 6, Folder 265)
  - SDS New Left Notes, Vol. 4, Nos. 25-31 (Box 6, Folder 266)
  - Save Our State, June 1971 (Box 6, Folder 267)
  - SLAM (Southern Legal Action Movement), Vol. 2, No. 4 (Box 6, Folder 268)
  - Southern Africa, Vol. 1, Nos. 6, 8-10; Vol. 2, No. 3; Vol. 3, Nos. 5-7; Vol. 4, Nos. 1-2 (Box 6, Folder 269)
  - Southern Africa Bulletin, No. 9 (Box 6, Folder 270)
  - The Southern Patriot, Vol. 17, No. 10;; Vol. 25, Nos. 7, 8; Vol. 28, No. 4; Vol. 29, No. 10 (Box 6, Folder 271)
  - The Spectator, Vol. 9, No. 5 (Box 6, Folder 272)
  - Steel, Spring 1971 (Box 6, Folder 273)
  - The Student Mobilizer, Vol. 1, Nos. 3-5; Vol. 2, Nos. 1-3, 5 (Box 6, Folder 274)
  - Union Democracy in Action, Nos. 37, 42 (Box 6, Folder 275)
  - Vietnam Courier, No. 111 (Box 6, Folder 276)
  - Vietnam Summer News, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-5 (Box 6, Folder 277)
  - The Virginia Weekly, Vol. 5, Nos. 1-8, 10; Vol. 6, No. 5 (Box 6, Folder 278)
  - Vocations for Social Change, June 1968-January 1969 (Box 6, Folder 279)
    Four volumes
  - Voice From The Cellar, Issue V (Box 6, Folder 280)
  - War Resisters League News, November/December 1963-March/June 1968 (Box 6, Folder 281)
    Four issues in total.
  - The West Virginia Activist, Vol. 1, Nos. 4-6 (Box 6, Folder 282)
  - The West Virginia AFL CIO Observer, Vol. 1, Nos. 9, 10, 12; Vol. 2, Nos. 1-2, 4-5 (Box 6, Folder 283)
  - WFDY News, Nos. 9-10, Year 1971; No. 1, Year 1972 (Box 6, Folder 284)
  - WIN, Vol. 2, Nos. 20-21 (Box 6, Folder 285)
  - World Youth, No. 6, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 286)
  - Young Worker, February and November 1971 (Box 6, Folder 287)
- Newspaper Clippings, VI.
  The Newspaper Clippings series is comprised of news clippings arranged topically. Topics include: Appalachia, black lung, coal miners, mining disasters and safety, political candidates, strikes, and West Virginia.
  - Appalachian Research and Defense Fund (Box 7, Folder 288)
  - Black Lung (Box 7, Folder 289)
  - Black Lung (Box 7, Folder 289a)
  - Black Lung (Box 7, Folder 290)
  - Black Lung (Box 7, Folder 290a)
  - Black Lung regarding Dr. Hawey A. Wells (Box 7, Folder 291)
  - Black Miners (Box 7, Folder 292)
  - Boyle, W. A. (Tony) (Box 7, Folder 293)
  - Buff, Dr. Isadore E. (Box 7, Folder 294)
  - Calleo, Basil A. - US Presidential candidate, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 295)
  - Coal (Box 7, Folder 296)
  - Coal Mine Safety and Cleaner Air Research (Box 7, Folder 297)
  - Coal Miners (Box 7, Folder 298)
  - Consolidated (Consol No. 9) Coal Company regarding opening of Consol No. 9 at Farmington, West Virginia (Box 7, Folder 299)
  - Disabled Miners of Southern West Virginia (Box 7, Folder 300)
  - Eastern Coal Company (Box 7, Folder 301)
  - Ecology in mines, industrial, and related areas (Box 7, Folder 302)
  - Economics of coal production:Encompassing the economy of the nation (Box 7, Folder 303)
  - Energy Shortage and the Development of New Coal Reserves (Box 7, Folder 304)
  - Energy Shortage and the Development of New Coal Reserves SI (Box 7, Folder 305)
  - Environmental Pollution by Mining Operations (acids and smoke) (Box 7, Folder 306)
  - Organization of Foreman's Union (Box 7, Folder 307)
  - U.S. Rep. Ken Hechler (Box 7, Folder 308)
  - Steve Kochis, Jr., US Presidential candidate, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 309)
  - Lewis, John L. (Box 7, Folder 310)
  - Manpower and training, UtS, Governmental Projects, etc. (Box 7, Folder 311)
  - Marsh, Don (Staff writer for the Charleston Gazette) - A series of articles on the human factor in mining (Box 7, Folder 312)
  - Sen. George McGovern Presidential campaign, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 313)
  - Mine Disaster, explosions, etc. (Box 7, Folder 314)
  - Mine Disaster, explosions, etc. II (Box 7, Folder 315)
  - Mine Disaster, (Daily World news clips) (Box 7, Folder 316)
  - Mine Regulation (Box 7, Folder 317)
  - Mine Safety (Box 7, Folder 318)
  - Mine Safety and Health: In regard to Black Lung (2nd of 3) (Box 7, Folder 319)
  - Mine Safety (Black Lung) (3rd of 3), 1969 (Box 7, Folder 320)
  - Miners for Democracy (MFD) (Box 7, Folder 321)
  - Strikes (Box 7, Folder 322)
  - Strike at Humphrey No. 7 regarding the posting of work vacancies, August 25, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 323)
  - Strip Mining (Box 7, Folder 324)
  - Strip Mining (2nd of 3) (Box 7, Folder 325)
  - Strip Mining (3rd of 3) (Box 7, Folder 326)
  - UNWA 1969 Elections: Joseph Yablonski, etc. (Box 7, Folder 327)
  - OMCA Welfare and Retirement Fund (Box 7, Folder 328)
  - UMWA, District 5 (Box 7, Folder 329)
  - West Virginia Labor Federation (Box 7, Folder 330)
  - West Virginia Legislature (Box 7, Folder 331)
  - West Virginia University (Box 7, Folder 332)
  - WVU Emergency Black Lung Committee (Box 7, Folder 333)
  - Elijah Wolford, Presidential Candidate for UMW, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 334)
  - Yablonski, murder of (Box 7, Folder 335)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 336)
- Photographs, VII.
  The Photographs series is comprised of prints and negatives related to coal mining and student unrest.
  - Coal Mining Facilities (Box 7, Folder 337)
  - Coal Mining families; homes; towns; cemetery (Box 7, Folder 337)
  - Mine Widows protest march around Oliver Plaza, Pittsburgh Pa., circa 1971 (Box 7, Folder 339)
  - WVU students support black lung research (Box 7, Folder 340)
  - Student war protest and draft card burning (Box 7, Folder 341)
  - Negatives. Mononpah, Colorado mine disaster and labor unrest, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 342)
  - Unidentified Photographs (Box 7, Folder 343)